Guide to the New Haven Hospital and Grace-New Haven Community Hospital Collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
New Haven Hospital and Grace-New Haven Community Hospital Collection
1826-1976
1911-1947
Ms Coll 43
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
2.5
(5 boxes)
This collection includes the Dean of the Yale School of Medicine's correspondence and copies of minutes and reports concerning New Haven Hospital, the New Haven Dispensary, and Grace-New Haven Community Hospital; broadsides and brochures concerning these institutions and Yale-New Haven Hospital;miscellaneous materials including historical accounts of the hospital; and newspaper clippings.
Bayne-Jones, Stanhope, 1888-1970
Blake, Francis G. (Francis Gilman), 1887-1952
Blumer, George, 1872-1962
Winternitz, M. C. (Milton C.), 1885-1959
Grace-New Haven Community Hospital
New Haven Hospital (New Haven, Conn.)
Yale-New Haven Hospital
Yale University. School of Medicine
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Deans' correspondence files in this collection were maintained and donated by Lottie G. Bishop, Executive Secretary in the Dean's Office. Some early broadsides, in particular, the Knight Hospital memoranda, were donated by the Beinecke Library in 1989. Some of the clippings and brochures appear to have been collected by Madeline Stanton, Librarian of the Historical Library. Some pamphlets were found in uncataloged pamphlet boxes that were transferred to the Yale Medical Library from Sterling Memorial Library. Most of these materials had previously been brought together by Madeline Stanton, former Librarian of the Historical Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
New Haven Hospital, originally known as the State Hospital, was organized in 1826 by professors at the Medical Institution of Yale College and other interested citizens. It was the first general hospital in the state and among the earliest general hospitals in the nation. After funds were raised, a building was erected on Cedar Street and opened in 1833. Donors became members of the General Hospital Society of Connecticut. The hospital did not have a direct relationship to the Yale School of Medicine until 1914 when an agreement allowed the hospital to be used for medical instruction and provided for the professors of the medical school to become chairs of the departments of the hospital. As the institution was still largely a charity in the first decades of the twentieth century, only Yale staff had access to patients. So that other physicians could gain clinical experience and follow their patients into the hospital, two other hospitals were founded in New Haven, Grace Hospital in 1889 and the Hospital of Saint Raphael in 1907 (opened 1910). Grace Hospital was founded by homeopaths and eclectics, but had become a community hospital by the 1920s. A plan to merge Grace Hospital with New Haven Hospital was avoided by Grace Hospital's raising enough money to remain independent. In 1944, discussions resumed resulting in a merger under the name Grace-New Haven Community Hospital in mid-1945. This hospital was partly under the control of the Yale School of Medicine but also open to community physicians. Grace-New Haven Community Hospital became Yale-New Haven Hospital in 1965. The New Haven Dispensary, founded independently in 1872, became, by contract in 1879, the clinic for the Yale University School of Medicine. It eventually became the outpatient department of the hospital.
Scope and Contents
Series 1 consists of files of the Dean of the Yale School of Medicine (George Blumer, Milton C. Winternitz, Stanhope Bayne Jones, and Francis G. Blake) concerning the New Haven Hospital and its successor, the Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, as well as on the New Haven Dispensary. These files include Executive Committee meetings, medical staff meetings; correspondence; reports on activities, finances, and personnel; and dicussions on the merger of New Haven Hospital and Grace Hospital. Series 2 consists of broadsides, pamphlets, and mailings related to the hospital. These go back to a small sheet in 1826 announcing a meeting to found a hospital. Of special note is a set of forms used by the Hospital from 1926 to 1938. Series 3 includes miscellaneous reports, reminiscences about working in the hospital, and other historical items. Series 4 contains a collection of newspaper clippings related to the hospital.
Arrangement
Organized in 4 series: 1. Deans' files: correspondence, minutes, and reports. 2. Printed broadsides and brochures. 3. Miscellany. 4. Newspaper clippings. Arrangement within series is roughly chronological.
Dispensaries -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Hospitals -- Accounting; Hospitals -- Administration; Hospitals -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Hospitals -- Finance; Tuberculosis -- Hospitals; Bishop, Lottie Genevieve, 1885-; Snoke, Albert W. (Albert Waldo), 1907-; Hill Health Center (New Haven, Conn.); Knight General Hospital (New Haven, Conn.); New Haven Dispensary (New Haven, Conn.)
- Deans' files: correspondence, minutes, and reports, 1911-1947; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This material is from the "chron file" maintained by Lottie Genevieve Bishop, who donated it to the Historical Library. Bishop, a graduate of Mt. Holyoke College in 1906, began to work as a secretary at Yale in 1911. She served as Executive Secretary in the Yale School of Medicine from 1928 until her retirement in 1953.
  - New Haven Hospital and New Haven Dispensary, 1911-1945; Subseries 1
    - Correspondence of George Blumer on the New Haven Dispensary, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      George Blumer was Dean of the Yale School of Medicine from 1910 to 1920. The folder contains correspondence with Yale Secretary George Parmly Day, Yale Treasurer Anson Phelps Stokes, and others, on the staffing and expenditures of the New Haven Dispensary.
    - Correspondence of George Blumer on the New Haven Dispensary, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence of Milton Winternitz on the centennial of the General Hospital Society of Connecticut, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Milton C. Winternitz was Dean of the Medical School from 1920 to 1935.
    - Correspondence of Milton Winternitz on a proposed merger of New Haven Hospital and Grace Hospital, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Major correspondents include James T. Moran, President of the General Hospital Society of Connecticut, and representatives of the Grace Hospital Society, C.-E. A. Winslow, Professor of Public Health, and John L. Rice, Health Officer of New Haven. See Box 5, folders 1 and 2.
    - Correspondence of Milton Winternitz on a proposed merger of New Haven Hospital and Grace Hospital, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Included are typescripts, "Report re New Haven Hospital and Dispensary," March 12, 1938; and Michael M. Davis with the assistance of Leonard Greenburg and Louise W. Farnam, "Report on Medical Institutions in New Haven," March 1928.
    - Correspondence of Milton Winternitz on a porposed merger of New Haven Hospital and Grace Hospital, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Discussion of a merger ended when Grace Hospital managed to raise enough funds to avoid merger. The issue reappeared in 1944-1945. See related newspaper clippings in Box 5, folder 1.
    - "The Relation of New Haven Hospital to the General Hospital Situation in New Haven", 1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Copy of a typescript written from the perspective of New Haven Hospital. No author is attributed.
    - Reports and statistics of the New Haven Dispensary, 1929-1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Proposals by Yale to the Josiah Macy Foundation to study the economics of hospital care, 1931 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - H. Gilbert Francke, "Survey of the Personnel Problems of the New Haven Hospital", 1932 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Reports of Camp Happyland/William Wirt Winchester Hospital, 1927-1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      The William Wirt Winchester Hospital was the tuberculosis hospital of New Haven Hospital. It was located on the grounds of the current VA Hospital in West Haven. Camp Happyland was a summer camp on the grounds of the William Wirt Hospital for the prevention of tuberculosis among children (a "preventorium"). See also Box 5, folder 4.
    - John Schoolcraft, "New Haven Hospital", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      With letter from Schoolcraft to Stanhope Bayne-Jones, dated July 13, 1938. Bayne-Jones served as Dean of the Yale School of Medicine from 1935 to 1940.
    - "The New Haven Dispensary, Founded 1872: A Statement of its History, Services, and Needs", 1939 March (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Carbon copy of a typescript.
    - New Haven Hospital, "Blood Banking Procedures", 1940 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "New Haven Hospital and New Haven Dispensary: Next Steps in Development", 1940 April (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Sent to Stanhope Bayne-Jones by John Schoolcraft, May 8, 1940.
    - Irma Biehusen, "A Study of the Health Service for Personnel of the New Haven Hospital", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Sent to Stanhope Bayne-Jones by James A. Hamilton, Director of New Haven Hospital, May 9, 1940. Biehusen, who collaborated with the hospital administration on this report, used it for her dissertation for her Yale Masters of Public Health.
    - "New Haven Hospital Defense Program", 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Mimeograph emergency plans for civilian defense during the war.
    - Correspondence of Francis G. Blake on New Haven Hospital, 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Francis G. Blake served as Dean of the Yale School of Medicine from 1941 to 1947.
    - Correspondence of Francis G. Blake on the New Haven Dispensary, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Minutes of the Executive Committee of New Haven Hospital, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Deans Stanhope Bayne-Jones and Francis G. Blake were members of the Executive Committee.
    - Minutes of the Executive Committee of New Haven Hospital, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Minutes of the Executive Committee of New Haven Hospital, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Minutes of the Medical Board of New Haven Hospital, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Minutes of the Medical Board of New Haven Hospital, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence of Francis G. Blake on the merger of New Haven Hospital and Grace Hospital, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence of Francis G. Blake on the merger of New Haven Hospital and Grace Hospital, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1945-1947; Subseries 2
    - Contract of Grace-New Haven Community Hospital with Yale University, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Correspondence of Francis G. Blake, Dean of the Medical School.
    - Building fund for Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Appointment of the Director of Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Dr. Albert W. Snoke was selected.
    - Miscellaneous correspondence of Francis G. Blake on Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Minutes of the Executive Committee of Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      These begin with an organizational meeting of the newly appointed board on July 27, 1945.
    - Minutes of the Executive Committee of Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Minutes of the Executive Committee of Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Minutes of the Joint Staff Executive Committee of Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Printed broadsides and brochures, 1826-1976; Series II
  - Notice of a meeting to discuss founding a "General State Hospital", 1826 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Print signature of William Leffingwell, President of the Board of Directors. The meeting was to be held on April 9 [1826].
  - "An Act to establish a State Hospital" (photostat), 1826 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Copy of the handwritten charter made by the Secretary of State's office for John Schoolcraft and given to Lottie G. Bishop in 1940
  - Fundraising broadsides, 1830-1834 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Gift of the Beinecke Library, 1989.
  - Membership certificate for the General Hospital Society of Connecticut, 1834 April 11 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Made out to John Skinner who paid twenty dollars to become a member for life.
  - Fundraising circular, [1847-1853] (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Print signature by Jonathan Knight.
  - Knight U.S.A. General Hospital, "General Orders", 1864-1865 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    During the Civil War, New Haven Hospital was converted to military use and was known as Knight Hospital. The folder contains one-page printed memoranda from Pliny A. Jewett, "Surgeon U. S. V., Comd'g Hospital."
  - Fundraising broadside, 1869 December (Box 3, Folder 7)
    The General Assembly granted the Hospital Society of Connecticut $20,000 on condition that a like amount could be raised by private donations. Printed signatures of William W. Boardman, Yale Medical Dean Charles A. Lindsley, and Horace Day.
  - Hospital formularies, 1880, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Appeal for funds and donation form, 1880 April (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Flyers for Hospital Sunday, 1881-1893 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    All but the first two flyers were transferred by the Beinecke Library. Hospital Sunday was an annual fundraiser for the Hospital.
  - Circular to raise funds for laundry machinery, 1886 October (Box 3, Folder 11)
    This would replace hand washing and save money.
  - The Farnam Ward of New Haven Hospital, ca. 1888-1889 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    [New Haven, n.d] Another copy of this brochure has been individually cataloged.
  - Charity Ball for the benefit of New Haven Hospital, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Catalogue of Books in the New Haven Hospital Library, 1896 September 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    These appear to be books for patients and are listed under such categories as Adventure and Travel, Biography, Fiction, etc.
  - Fundraising broadside, 1902 September 13 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    From the Prudential Committee consisting of Charles Ray Palmer, Charles E. Graves, and William G. Daggettt.
  - "By-Laws" and "Rules" of New Haven Hospital, n.d. and 1907 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Brochures and miscellany, 1919-1929 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Includes brochures on the new buildings of the New Haven Hospital including the Private Pavilion, Brady Memorial Laboratory, Lauder Hall, and the Farnam Memorial Building; and a Yale University News statement announcing that the General Education Board of the Rockerfeller Foundation had given two million dollars for a new laboratory and for the Clinic building. There is also a pamphlet, "Information Relative to Interneship" (1927) with notes on revision for a later year.
  - Raleigh Fitkin Memorial Building brochures and memorabilia, 1929-1930 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Includes copy of the typescript "'Minutes of the Meeting of the Committee on the dedication of the Raleigh Fitkin Memorial," December 20, 1929.
  - Camp Happyland/ William Wirth Winchester Hospital brochures, 1929-1935 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    The William Wirt Winchester Hospital, part of New Haven Hospital, was founded in 1911 at the site of what is now the VA Hospital in West Haven. It treated patients with tuberculosis. Camp Happyland, a summer camp for children on the hospital grounds, provided outdoor activities for children in an effort to prevent tuberculosis.
  - Brochures and miscellany, 1930-1934 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Includes "Information Relative to Internship," 1933.
  - New Haven Hospital forms, 1926, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    A wide variety of hospital forms for admitting and discharging patients, requesting tests, recording patient care, reporting deaths, ordering supplies, regulations for visitors, applications for interneship, etc.
  - New Haven Hospital forms, 1933, 1938, and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - New Haven Hospital pamphlet series, 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Series of eleven illustrated public information pamphlets on New Haven Hospital including pamphlets on infantile paralysis, x-ray facilities, and Camp Happyland.
  - "Out Patient Department of the New Haven Hospital (New Haven Dispensary), Schedule of Clinics", 1933, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Brochures and miscellany, 1935-1939 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Brochures and miscellany, 1940-1945 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Community Hospital News, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital brochures and miscellany, 1945-1949 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Includes a Resident Staff Manual for 1949.
  - Grace-New Haven Commmunity Hospital brochures and miscellany, 1950-1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital and Yale-New Haven Medical Center brochures and miscellany, 1955-1959 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    The Yale-New Haven Medical Center was incorporated in 1955. Folder includes material on the dedication of the Hunter Radiation Therapy Building, 1958.
  - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital and Yale-New Haven Medical Center brochures and miscellany, 1960-1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Yale News release on the formation of Yale-New Haven Hospital, 1965 March 23 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Yale-New Haven Hospital brochures and miscellany, 1965-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Internship and residency brochures, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Yale-New Haven Hospital sesquicentennial celebration, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous materials, 1894-1968; Series III
  This series includes non-published material from sources other than the Dean's files.
  - Postmortem examination at New Haven Hospital and possibly related materials, 1894 and n.d. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Postmortem examination of John Barber, a black man, by Moses C. White at request of the coroner. This case appeared to have led to criticism in the press and a call for an investigation. These materials were donated by Dr. Frederick N. Sperry from the library of Dr. Henry L. Swain, 1944.
  - Lybrand, Ross Bros. & Montgomery, "New Haven Hospital: Report on Survey of Certain Accounting Methods", 1921 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Painted drawing: "New Haven Hospital, 37,000 Days of Free Care in 1933", ca. 1933 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Hospitals and Medicine", 1937 September (Box 4, Folder 11)
    A mimeograph history of New Haven Hospital by the Community Chest and the Council of Social Agencies, New Haven. The folder also contains a typed extract on the Hospital from a published article on the history of the Connecticut Medical Society in 1892.
  - Henry R. Viets, National Association for Infantile Paralysis, "Notes on the New Haven Epidemic, 1943", 1943 August 20 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Polio patients were treated at the New Haven Hospital. Sent to the Historical Library at the request of John F. Fulton.
  - "I Remember When" - personal reminisences of New Haven Hospital, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    These were assembled by J. H. Wallace and included two deans of the Yale School of Nursing, and various employees of the hospital. There is also a detailed timeline of the history of New Haven Hospital.
  - John F. Fulton, "Notes on the History of Grace-New Haven Community Hospital and the General Hospital Society of Connecticut", 1953 December 11 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Talk in the Fitkin Amphitheater to the Board of Directors of Grace-New Haven Community Hospital.
  - C. C. Bishop, Report of the Department of Surgery, Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1954, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Lists of officers, directors, and advisory boards, 1959-1968, 1968 November (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Requested by Lottie G. Bishop, office of the Secretary, Yale University, and supplied by Richard H. Judd, Assistant Director of Yale-New Haven Hospital.
  - AFL-CIO flyer, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Concerning unionizing Grace-New Haven Community Hospital employees.
- Newspaper clippings, 1927-1969; Series IV
  Newspaper clippings pasted on paper sheets. These appear to have come from more than one source.
  - Proposed merger of New Haven Hospital and Grace Hospital, 1927-1929 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    These clippings were pasted in a binder. See Box 1, folders 5 and 6.
  - Proposed mergerof New Haven Hospital and Grace Hospital, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous clippings on health and medicine in New Haven, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Camp Happyland/William Wirt Winchester Hospital, 1931-1933 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    See also Box 1, folder 11.
  - New Haven Hospital, 1929-1939 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - New Haven Hospital and Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1940-1949 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital, 1951-1963 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Yale-New Haven Hospital, 1966-1969 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Hill Health Center, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    A number of physicians associated with Yale-New Haven Hospital opposed this government-funded community health center in New Haven.